Guide to the Liane Ellison Norman Papers, 1952-2008 AIS.2010.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Liane Ellison Norman Papers
1955-2008
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Norman, Liane Ellison
AIS.2010.02
3.75 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Liane Ellison Norman is a Pittsburgh writer who has contributed articles, editorials, columns, and book reviews to a number of local and national publications. A majority of the collection consists of her work which deals mostly with social issues, war, violence, and the hazards of nuclear energy. The collection also includes correspondence with publishers, writers and agents.
Biography
Liane Ellison Norman can be described as an author, essayist, columnist, poet, professor, fundraiser, and social activist. Born in Ogden, Utah, in 1937, her interest in writing followed her through life when in 1959 she earned her bachelor's degree from Grinnell College in English and in 1967 obtained her MA in English and PhD in English and American Literature from Brandeis University. She moved to Pittsburgh, Pa., in the 1967 to teach English at Chatham College (now Chatham University). In 1970, she began teaching part-time at the University of Pittsburgh and seven years later she was hired as a full-time faculty member in the English department. While in Pittsburgh she has contributed her writing to both local and national publications like the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, The Pittsburgh New Sun, The New York Times, The Center Magazine, Sojourners, and Friends Journal, just to name a few. Her work approaches social justice issues, conflict, civil disobedience, nuclear issues, and politics. She has also written extensively about classical music. In 1984 she founded and acted as director of the Pittsburgh Peace Institute, an organization committed to teaching non-violent solutions to youth and adults. She authored a number of books: Stitches in the Air: A Novel about Mozart's Mother, The Duration of Grief, Hammer of Justice: Molly Rush and the Plowshares 8, and A Simpleton Story: A Fairy Tale for the Nuclear Age.
Scope and Content Notes
The Liane Ellison Norman Papers include writings published between 1955 and 2008. These include high school and college writings; her doctoral dissertation; drafts and published copies of essays, columns, articles and editorials published in local and national publications; and unpublished manuscripts. Also included is correspondence between agents, editors, and publishers.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Liane Ellison Norman in February 2010.
Related Material
Pittsburgh Peace Institute Records, 1984-1997, AIS.1998.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Thomas Merton Center Records, 1971-2004, AIS.1982.19, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
I. Writings, 1952- 2008
II. Correspondence, 1972-1988
Previous Citation
Liane Ellison Norman Papers, 1955-2008, AIS.2010.02, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh post-gazette (Pittsburgh, Pa.: 1927); Political activists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; War -- Moral and ethical aspects -- History; Peace movements -- Pennsylvania; Society of Friends; Pittsburgh post-gazette (Pittsburgh, Pa.: 1978); Personal papers; Women; Social action; Nuclear disarmament; Peace movements -- United States; Authors, American -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh Peace Institute; University of Pittsburgh. Department of English -- Faculty; Brandeis University; Grinnell College; Norman, Liane Ellison
- Writings, 1952-2008; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series includes material written between 1955-2008, such as drafts, research materials and notes, final published works, high school and college writings, her PhD dissertation, and unpublished manuscripts. It is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - The Active Reader, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Adult Shares Liberated Feelings", Pitt News, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "An African-American man gave his heart for a peaceful community," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "All I want for Christmas," Pittsburgh Catholic, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Alternative to war must be found," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Angels of History," review of Harry Watson's Montana 1948 and Justice, Sojourner, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Another Tale of Two Cities," Pittsburgh New Sun, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "At the Rockwell Shareholders Meeting," In These Times, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Beans," Pittsburgh New Sun, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Bequest of Brutality: Stopping the Chain Reaction," Christian Science Monitor, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beyond the Bomb by: Mark Sommers, book review, The New People, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The Best Version of the Truth," Pitt News, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Breaking the Silence," Center Magazine, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Bringing Bacon Home," Pittsburgh New Sun, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Busing in a Joint-Stock World, Center Magazine, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Caged, Like Vietnamese, For Us All," New York Times, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Children's Literature in Pittsburgh," City Times, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Citizens Make a Peace System," Peace Review, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Civilization Meets Barbarity," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Claiming Breath," By: Diane Glancy, book review in Sistersong, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "The Clue in the Apple Tree," Pittsburgh New Sun, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Community and Reciprocity," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Companions Against the Storm," The Center Magazine, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "The Composition of Faith," Sojourners, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "The Conscience of the Community," Fellowship, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "The Court and Single Human Souls," The New York Times, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "The Cost of Credibility," Pittsburgh New Sun, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Constructive Nonviolence," The Acorn, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "A Cry for Help," Pittsburgh New Sun, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Daffodils for an Anniversary," Pittsburgh New Sun, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Deer Hunter, film review in The Mill Hunk Herald, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "The Delivery," in The City Times and The Progressive, 1980 and 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Don't Bomb Baghdad," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Don't Eradicate RAD," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Down on Vietnam Again," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Dying in Luxury," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Ecologists Studies in Utah Should Inspire More Research," The Salt Lake Tribune, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Epilogue written for Grinnell College yearbook, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Explanations of History," The Center Magazine, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Faith in a Secular Religion," review of Steve Nelson's American Radical, City Times, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "The Faith of Mysteries," Sojourners, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Fear is an Instinct for Survival," In These Times, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "Fighting Imaginary Wars," The Bulletin of Concerned Asian Scholars, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "For Unto you is Born this Day," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Four Pink Nuns", 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "Garden Thoughts: Healing the Wounded Land," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "Getting Along Without War," The Mill Hunk Herald, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "Girl from the Fifteenth Century," Harper's Weekly, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "God in a Dark Place," Friends Journal, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "Good Signs," The New People, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - "Idiots and Lunatics," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - "If it's Classified, You're a Spy," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "Ignorance and Grace," in Sojourners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "In a Bureaucratic Maze," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "Guest Lecturer from Vietnam," Los Angeles Times, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - "The Habit of Philanthropy," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "Hearing Music from the Inside," Early Music America, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "A High Standard of Living," Friends Journal and The Star, 1977,1979 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - "High Technology and the Peasants," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - "Holocaust Now," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - "Hugh Scott Meets Some Pennsylvania People," Harper's Weekly, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - "Hype and Misogyny," review of Susan Faludi's Backlash, Sojourners, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - "Importance of the Possible," The New People, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - In Their Far Away Country, undated (Box 1, Folder 64-66)
  - "Integrate to Make Whole," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Interfaith service on Martin Luther King's birthday at the Trinity Episcopal Church, Pittsburgh, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - "Inwit and Outlaw," The Acorn, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - "Issues Obscured at Spy Time," University Times, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - "The Judge and the Reporter on the Law and the Facts," Christianity and Crisis, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - "It Aint Never Happened Before," Literary Cavalcade, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - "Judge Hammered Justice for Plowshares 8," The New People, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - "Judge Stifles Plowshares 'Greater Evil' Defense," In These Times, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - "Justice Must be Scrupulous," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Keep, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Lessons of War," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - "Letters from the Allegheny County Jail to Magistrate", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - "Letter to President Bush," The Pittsburgh Post Gazette, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - License agreement for Molly Rush and the Plowshares 8, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - "The Life of Literature," The Center Magazine, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Lincoln Ellison and the Great Basin Experiment Station, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - "Living up to Molly," Christianity and Crisis, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - "Live a Little," The New York Times, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - "Loneliness of a Long-Distance Crusader," Christianity and Crisis, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - "Lunch with my Father," PHP, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - "The Making and Unmaking of War," The Center Magazine, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - "The Mammoth and the Buttercup," The Pittsburgh New Sun & Iowa Woman, 1980,1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "The Man Who Wanted to Write Fiction," Bulletin of Concerned Asian Scholars & The Pittsburgh Forum, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Memorial Day-1980," Friends Journal (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Molly Rush and the Plowshares 8: Heroes of our time," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Molly Rush Acted to Save her Children,"The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "More Carrots, No Appeasement," The New York Times, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Mozart's Mother: The Novel," Carnegie Magazine, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mozart's Women book review in Early Music America, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "The Nature of Midori," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - New York Times letter to the editor concerning George Bush, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Nicaraguans on their Revolution: We'll Never go Back," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Non-Profit Makes Money for All," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Nonviolent Alternative," The Center Magazine, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Non-Violent Defense," The Peacemaking Struggle: Militarism and Resistance, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Not too Busy," The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Novel as Moral Experiment: George Elliot's Novels, PhD thesis, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Novel Treasures," a review of Daniel Peter's Rising from the Ruins, Sojourners, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Nuremberg Sets Standards of Decency," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Of Story and Truth," Sojourners, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "On the Political Abuse of Language," The Los Angeles Times, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Once More into the Breach, Dear Friends, Once More," The Acorn, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ogden High School creative writing, undated (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - "One Woman, One Vote," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Our Libraries Need Our Help," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Overdue," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "A Parable for Our Time" special feature in The New York Times titled "One Woman's Voice", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Part Time: A Way Out of the Trap?" The Steel City Star, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "The Part-Time Worker's Time Has Come," The Los Angeles Times, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Peace Heroes in the 20th Century by Charles Debenedetti, book review in The Journal of American History, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Peace in Pittsburgh," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Peace Through Strength," The New People and Civilian Based Defense, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Pedestrian Students and High Flying Squirrels," The Center Magazine, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Pittsburgh-Plutonium Connection," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette "Roundtable", May 14,1986-July 16,1986 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "Plain as Courtesy," a review of Dorothy Holley's Late Day Thoughts on www.gentlyread.wordpress.com, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Point Reyes Light, "In Other Words" column, May 9, 1974-August 1, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Point Reyes Light, "In Other Words" column, August 8,1974-September 16, 1974 and April 19,1979 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "Political Conventions, Public Good," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazett e, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - "The 'Politics of Love' in the Cause for Peace," The Center Magazine, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - "Power and the People," The New People, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - "A Power Rate for the People," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "Prelude to Winter," a play in three acts written at Grinnell College, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - "Prospects for Integration: Penalized for Success," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - "Put the Money Where Your Music Is: A Blueprint for Successful Early Music Fundraising," Early Music America, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "The Quiet Virtues: Jane Austen's Moral Universe," Sojourners, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Reader, I Married Him and The American Eve in Fact and Fiction, book reviews in Nineteenth Century Fiction, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - "Recovering: a review essay of four books on the Indochina War," Bulletin of Concerned Asian Scholars, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - "Remembering Advice From Long Ago Regarding Ethical Land Use," Ogden Standard Examiner, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "Renewal," a letter written for the Pittsburgh Friends meeting, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - "Resting Easy," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - "Reverence for the Word of God," review of Peter Gome's The Good Book, Sojourners, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "Risk and Redundancy," Publication of the Modern Language Association of America, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "The Rockwell International Shareholders' Meeting, 1982" Friends Journal (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "The Sacrificial Lamb's Version," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - "Searching For Alternatives to the Nuclear Arms Race," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - "The Season of Waiting," The New People, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - "The Secret History of Acid," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - "The Selective Conscience," The Duquesne Law Review, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - "Selective Conscientious Objection," The Center Magazine, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - "Selling the Atom," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - "A Sense of Justice," The Center Magazine, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Simpleton Story: A Fairy Tale For a Nuclear Age, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Simpleton Story, draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - "Skokie: Point of Reconciliation," The Steel City Star, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - "The Snows of Yesteryear," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette and Winning Medals at Snow Basin," a slightly different in The Salt Lake City Tribune, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - "Spanking: The Course of Most Resistance," The Los Angeles Times and Parents Anonymous Frontiers, 1974,1978 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - "The Spell of War," The Center Magazine, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - "The Spider's Secret," The Center Magazine, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - "Star Chamber: Academic Integrity on Trial," Pennsylvania American Association of University Professors newsletter and The New People, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - "The Steel Drivin' Man," one act play written for Grinnell college playwriting class, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - "Stern's Message to China is Universal," In These Times, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - "Survivors," The Steel City Star, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - "Taking Heart: Reflection on School Desegregation," The New People, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - "A Test of Will," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - "Things I Can't Afford," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Three Children's Books for Civilian-Based Defense," in ATS Newsletter, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Through A Glass Darkly, college honors project, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Unwanted Pregnancy from the Perspective of Nonviolence," By: Liane Ellison Norman and Marie Norman, presented at the International Symposium on Public Policies Towards Unwanted Pregnancies, University of Pittsburgh, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "War's Civilian Casualties," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "War Must, Very Simply, Be Abolished," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "The Way It Is," City Times, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "We The Government," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Whale In The Rice Paddy and Other Essays, preface and chapter 1, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Whale In The Rice Paddy and Other Essays, chapter 2, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Whale In The Rice Paddy and Other Essays, chapters 3-4, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "The Whale In The Rice Paddy," Bulleting of Concerned Asian Scholars, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "What's Going On In Nicaragua?" The Pittsburgh Post- Gazette, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "What Have We Done To Iraq," The Pittsburgh Post- Gazette, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "What Is Life Really About," a speech delivered at Grinnell College Reunion, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "What Is A Whale Good For," Marin Life, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "What I Want From The Democrats," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "What's So Special About Jesus," Friends Journal, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "What Will We Do In Our Town," The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "The Wonderful History of Sauerkraut," The Pittsburgh New Sun, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Writers For Life," The Center Magazine, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Writing Mozart's Mother," Sistersong, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Various articles on Vietnam, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Various writings from high school and college, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, 1972-1988; II.
  This series includes correspondence written between 1972-1988 with publishers, editors, and agents concerning book publications.
  - The Active Reader, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Whale in the Rice Paddy, 1973-1990 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Numerous agents, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Gerald McCauley Agency, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - The Fox Chase Agency, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - In Their Far Away Country, 1976-1990 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - The Walter Pitkin Agency, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - In The Last Days aka Molly Rush and The Plowshares 8, 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Television production of Molly Rush and the Plowshares 8, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 33)